[
    {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "다음 글의 목적으로 가장 적절한 것은? We hope this notice finds you in good health and high  spirits. We are writing to inform you that a package was  delivered to the Rosehill Apartment Complex on October 9th,  specifically addressed to your home. However, despite  multiple attempts to deliver the package to you, it has  remained unclaimed at our front desk for an extended period.  As the management office, it is our responsibility to ensure  the safekeeping of all delivered items and help deliver them  quickly to the right residents. Therefore, we kindly request  that you visit the management office during our office hours  to claim your package. We genuinely appreciate your  cooperation in this matter.",
        "choices": [
            "관리 사무실 공사 일정을 알리려고",
            "배달된 물품을 찾아갈 것을 요청하려고",
            "잘못 찾아간 물품의 반납을 부탁하려고",
            "배달 물품의 도난 방지 조치를 설명하려고",
            "관리 사무실 운영 시간 변경을 공지하려고"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "다음 글에 드러난 ‘I’의 심경 변화로 가장 적절한 것은? I hurried to the bus terminal to return home for Christmas.  As soon as I arrived at the terminal, I saw my bus pulling  away. I called out and ran after the bus, but it was too late.  I felt a wave of disappointment wash over me as I realized  that I would have to wait three hours for the next bus. I  must have been visibly upset because a woman came over,  took my arm, and led me to the street. She called a taxi and  gave the driver a five­dollar bill. She told him to take me to  the ferry terminal, because the bus made a stop there before  heading out onto the highway. She also wished me a Merry  Christmas, and all I could do was smile. I couldn’t believe  what she had done for me, a complete stranger!",
        "choices": [
            "frustrated → touched",
            "jealous → proud",
            "thrilled → doubtful",
            "calm → regretful",
            "indifferent → sympathetic"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "다음 글에서 필자가 주장하는 바로 가장 적절한 것은? The chemists Hans Ebel, Claus Bliefert, and William Russey  note: “It goes without saying that scientists need to be skillful  readers. Extensive reading is the principal key to expanding  one’s knowledge and keeping up with developments in a  discipline. However, what is often overlooked here is that  scientists are also obliged to be skillful writers. Only the  researcher  who  is  competent  in  the  art  of  written  communication can play an active and effective role in  contributing to science.” From the perspective of readability,  moreover, scientists should always write with a reader­centered  mentality; even in the act of writing they must be mindful of  the act of reading. It would be beneficial for them to  understand how readers read in order to improve their writing.",
        "choices": [
            "과학자는 독자와 만나는 기회를 자주 가져야 한다.",
            "과학자는 독자의 관점에서 글을 쓸 줄 알아야 한다.",
            "과학자는 다양한 의견에 개방적인 태도를 가져야 한다.",
            "과학자는 자기 연구 분야 이외의 책도 많이 읽어야 한다.",
            "과학자는 연구 결과가 사회에 미치는 영향을 인식해야 한다.\n\n고3\n영어영역\n3\n3\n8"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "밑줄 친 squeeze economies into a test tube가 다음 글에서  의미하는 바로 가장 적절한 것은?  Physicians and other natural scientists test their theories  using controlled experiments. Macroeconomists, however,  have no laboratories and little ability to run economy­wide  experiments of any kind. Granted, they can study different  economies around the world, but each economy is unique, so  comparisons are tricky. Controlled experiments also provide  the natural sciences with something seldom available to  economists — the chance, or serendipitous, discovery (such as  penicillin). Macroeconomists studying the U.S. economy have  only one patient, so they can’t introduce particular policies in  a  variety  of  alternative  settings.  You  can’t  squeeze  economies into a test tube. Cries of “Eureka!” are seldom  heard from macroeconomists. An economy consisting of  hundreds of millions of individual actors is a complicated  thing. As Nobel Prize­winning physicist Murray Gell­Mann  once observed, “Think how hard physics would be if particles  could think.” * serendipitous: 우연히 발견하는",
        "choices": [
            "admit economists’ contributions to the natural sciences",
            "conduct controlled experiments on the economy",
            "employ complex economic theories",
            "share test results with other scientists",
            "collect economic data over a long period of time"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "다음 글의 요지로 가장 적절한 것은? Imagine a movie where nothing but terrible things happen.  But, in the end, everything works out. Everything is  resolved. A sufficiently happy ending can change the meaning  of all the previous events. They can all be viewed as  worthwhile, given that ending. Now imagine another movie. A  lot of things are happening. They’re all exciting and  interesting. But there are a lot of them. Ninety minutes in,  you start to worry. “This is a great movie,” you think, “but  there are a lot of things going on. I sure hope the filmmaker  can pull it all together.” But that doesn’t happen. Instead, the  story ends, suddenly, unresolved, or something facile and  clichéd occurs. You leave deeply annoyed and unsatisfied — failing to notice that you were fully engaged and enjoying  the movie almost the whole time you were in the theatre.  The present can change the past, and the future can change  the present. * facile: 지나치게 단순한  ** clichéd: 상투적인",
        "choices": [
            "결말에 따라 이전 상황에 대한 인식이 달라진다.",
            "익숙하지 않은 이야기는 대중의 사랑을 받기 어렵다.",
            "흥행에 성공한 영화가 항상 작품성이 뛰어난 것은 아니다.",
            "상황에 대한 집단의 평가는 개인의 평가에 영향을 끼친다.",
            "같은 영화를 반복적으로 보는 것이 영화에 대한 이해를 높인다."
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "다음 글의 주제로 가장 적절한 것은? [3점] Just as today some jobs are better than others, so would  they have been in early societies with their blossoming  towns and eventually cities, with some roles more dangerous  and some having more plentiful access to food or other  resources. The archeological record shows that soon after  the appearance of towns, agriculture, and surpluses, some  burials start to look different from others. Some individuals  are buried with more precious goods (metals, weapons, and  maybe even art), some are in group graves and some by  themselves, and still others don’t even seem to be buried at  all. The bones from the burials start to show us differences  as well — chemical and isotope analyses of teeth and long  bones reveal that some members of groups were getting  more protein or minerals than others; some have more  evidence of diseases and greater physical injuries from their  labors. Early on these differences are small, but by 5,000 to  7,000 years ago they are becoming quite pronounced. * archeological: 고고학의  ** surplus: 잉여물  *** isotope: 동위 원소",
        "choices": [
            "the evidence of social inequality found in ancient burials",
            "scientific efforts to preserve ancient remains",
            "attempts to overcome inequality in history",
            "cultural differences in the concept of better jobs",
            "ancient agricultural methods passed down to the present"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "다음 글의 제목으로 가장 적절한 것은? When you break up with a partner or close friend, the  natural response (after having a good cry, obviously) is to  blame yourself. You wonder what you did wrong and what  you might have done differently. Bonds can help us reach a  more balanced perspective; there are some bonds that were  simply never meant to last, even if they played an essential  role in your evolution to this point. Perhaps the most  valuable thing is to know that seeing bonds break doesn’t  have to break us. In chemistry, by definition, a change in the  atomic bonding is not just the end of one state, but the  beginning of another: creating the space for new bonding  potential. The same is true for us as humans. It might take  a cup of warm milk to reset us and give us comfort after a  relationship has broken down. But however many bonds we  see come apart, we will always retain one of our most  human abilities: to connect afresh, find new friends and love  again.",
        "choices": [
            "Relationships: The Older, The Better",
            "A Break in a Bond: A New Beginning",
            "Shared Experiences Make Strong Bonds",
            "A Friend in Need, A Friend Indeed",
            "Two Heads Are Better Than One\n\n4\n영어영역\n고3\n4\n8"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "다음 도표의 내용과 일치하지 않는 것은? How Naps Change As We Age The above graph shows the nap length and the number of  nap days per year by age group.",
        "choices": [
            "As people get older, the \nnap length consistently decreases, but that is not the case \nwith the number of nap days per year. 2. The 18 to 24 age \ngroup, which has the longest nap length, naps over 30 \nminutes longer than the 55 and older age group, which has \nthe shortest nap length. 3. As for the number of nap days \nper year, the 55 and older age group has the most days, \n135.7 days, whereas the 25 to 34 age group has the fewest \ndays, 84.8 days. 4. The 35 to 44 age group is ranked third \nin the nap length, and second in the number of nap days per \nyear. 5. The nap length and the number of nap days per \nyear of the 45 to 54 age group are lower than those of the \n35 to 44 age group."
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "question": "Ann Bancroft에 관한 다음 글의 내용과 일치하지 않는 것은? Ann Bancroft was born in Minnesota, U.S. Bancroft grew  up in rural Minnesota in what she described as a family of  risk­takers. Although she struggled with a learning disability,  she graduated from St. Paul Academy and became a physical  education teacher. Bancroft resigned her teaching position in  1986 in order to participate in the Will Steger International  Polar Expedition. The group departed from Ellesmere Island  on March 6, and after 56 days, she and five other team  members arrived at the North Pole by dogsled. She thus  became the first woman to reach the North Pole by sled and  on foot. In November 1992, she led three other women on  the American Women’s Expedition to Antarctica. It took  them 67 days to reach the South Pole on skis and Bancroft  became the first woman to have stood at both poles.",
        "choices": [
            "Minnesota의 시골에서 자랐다.",
            "St. Paul Academy를 졸업하고 체육 교사가 되었다.",
            "1986년에 교직을 그만두었다.",
            "Ellesmere섬에서 출발한 지 56일 후에 북극에 도달했다.",
            "세 명의 남자 대원과 남극까지 스키를 타고 갔다."
        ],
        "answer": 5
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "2023 Greenfield City Run에 관한 다음 안내문의 내용과 일치 하지 않는 것은? 2023 Greenfield City Run Are you eager for the race that can awaken the  running spirit within you? Maybe the Greenfield City Run  is best for you.  ∙When: Sunday, November 5  - Assembly time is 9:00 a.m.   - Start time is 9:30 a.m. ∙Where: Riverside Park ∙Races: 2km, 5km, 10km (The 2km race is only for kids.) ∙Registration  - Registration starts on October 16.  - The registration fees depend on the date you sign up. $30: October 16 - November 4 / $40: November 5  - Register online at www.finishrace.com. ∙Activities  - Coffee and Cookie Fair & Outdoor Charity Bazaar For more information, call (516) 703-1737.",
        "choices": [
            "집합 시간은 오전 9시이다.",
            "2km 종목은 아이들만 참가할 수 있다.",
            "등록은 10월 16일부터 시작된다.",
            "날짜와 상관없이 등록비는 동일하다.",
            "야외 자선 바자회가 있다."
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "Bluehill Apple Picking에 관한 다음 안내문의 내용과 일치하 는 것은? Bluehill Apple Picking Take home a bag full of apples fresh from the orchard.  This year, unfortunately, apple pie eating contests will  not be held due to time constraints. ∙Date: Saturday, October 21, 2023 ∙Time  - Departure: 8:15 a.m. for pre­trip meeting               Buses leave at 8:30 a.m. SHARP!   - Return: Approximately 7:00 p.m.  ∙Price: $20 per person  (transportation included, meals not included) ∙Pre­registration is required at www.blueapple.com.  - 12 years and under must be accompanied by adults.",
        "choices": [
            "애플파이 먹기 대회가 열릴 예정이다.",
            "버스는 오전 8시 15분에 출발한다.",
            "참가비에 식사가 포함되어 있다.",
            "사전 등록은 필요 없다.",
            "12세 이하는 성인이 동반해야 한다.\n\n고3\n영어영역\n5\n5\n8"
        ],
        "answer": 5
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "다음 글의 밑줄 친 부분 중, 어법상 틀린 것은? [3점] Dr. Joseph Bell was a professor of medicine at the  University of Edinburgh. His students were amazed by his  astonishing powers of observation. He seemed able to  determine what patients did for a living, or what illness",
        "choices": [
            "they \nmight have, simply by glancing in their direction. One time he \nconcluded that a patient 2. had walked across a golf course on \nthe way to the doctor, simply by looking at his shoes. One of \nBell’s students was particularly impressed with his teacher’s \nabilities. He filled up notebooks with examples of 3. what he \ncalled Bell’s “eerie trick of spotting details.” The student \neventually went into practice himself outside London. When \nbusiness was slow he filled his spare moments by writing \nstories. He took Dr. Bell’s powers of perception, and gave \nthem to a character of his own making — a character who \nmade the young doctor, Arthur Conan Doyle, 4. famous \naround the world. And so the professor who made even the \nmost complex diagnosis seem “elementary” 5. becoming the \ninspiration for fiction’s greatest detective, Sherlock Holmes. \n* eerie: 오싹한  ** diagnosis: 진단"
        ],
        "answer": 5
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "다음 글의 밑줄 친 부분 중, 문맥상 낱말의 쓰임이 적절하지  않은 것은? [3점] Technology has historically distinguished the way music is  produced. In a live jazz concert a bass player can provide  the audience with a ten­minute jam session but is",
        "choices": [
            "unable \nto do so if making a record. Time and space limits on early \ndiscs made this liberalized performance style impossible. \nOften, pieces would be separated into a number of discs \nleading to a 2. lack of continuity. In addition to length, \nmusicians had to take into account how the machinery \nrecorded and absorbed their sound. Especially in the early \ndays of recording, human voices as well as instruments \nwere often distorted once recorded. To prevent such \ndistortion, it was up to the musician to 3. alter the sound to \naccommodate the recording technology that was just coming \ninto existence. Jazz musicians and orchestras almost molded \ntheir works around recording parameters. Many musicians \nwere",
            "resistant \nto \nthe \nlimitations \nand \nbenefits \nof \ntechnology and created their records accordingly. The \nrecording limitations began to filter into stage performance. \nMusicians were restricted to three­minute songs in the \nrecording studio and they soon 5. kept their songs to that \nlength on stage too.\n* jam session: 즉흥 연주  ** mold: (틀에 맞추어) 만들다  \n*** parameter: 한도, 기준\n[31 ~ 34] 다음 빈칸에 들어갈 말로 가장 적절한 것을 고르시오."
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "question": "There’s reason to worry that an eyes­on­the­prize mentality  could be a mistake. Lots of research shows that we tend to  be over­confident about how easy it is to be self­disciplined.  This is why so many of us optimistically buy expensive gym  memberships when paying per­visit fees would be cheaper,  register for online classes we’ll never complete, and purchase  family­size chips on discount to trim our monthly snack  budget, only to consume every last crumb in a single sitting.  We think “future me” will be able to make good choices, but  too often “present me” gives in to temptation. People have a  remarkable ability to              their own failures. Even  when we flounder again and again, many of us manage to  maintain a rosy optimism about our ability to do better next  time rather than learning from our past mistakes. We cling to  fresh starts and other reasons to stay upbeat, which may help  us get out of bed in the morning but can prevent us from  approaching change in the smartest possible way.  * crumb: 부스러기  ** flounder: 실패하다  *** upbeat: 낙관적인",
        "choices": [
            "criticize",
            "remind",
            "ignore",
            "detect",
            "overestimate"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "The way we perceive the colors of the rainbow, and the  universe in general, is influenced by the words we use to  describe them. This is not limited to visual perception but also  applies to smell, taste, touch, our perception of time and  countless other human experiences. A wine or Scotch  connoisseur, for example, has a much richer vocabulary at their  disposal to describe the fullness, finish, flavors and aroma of  the drink, which in turn improves their ability to recognize and  remember subtle differences of which a non­expert may be  unaware. Similarly, a chef or perfumer has at their disposal  labels for flavors and smells that allow them to perceive,  differentiate among, prepare and remember subtle variations.  The labels that we have at our disposal influence how we see  the world around us. Regardless of where you place the limits  of linguistic effects on cognition, there is evidence that at  least some of the things that we perceive and remember differ  depending on                                   . [3점] * connoisseur: (예술품ㆍ음식ㆍ음악의) 감정가  ** cognition: 인식",
        "choices": [
            "where we purchase them",
            "how expensive they are",
            "what labels we use",
            "how persuasive ads are",
            "who makes the products\n\n6\n영어영역\n고3\n6\n8"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "question": "A connection with ancestors, especially remote ones, is  useful for getting a wide­angled, philosophical view of life.  Whereas our immediate ancestors are notably skilled at  helping us with the “little pictures,” namely the particular,  the trees — say, a problem with a boss — our remote ones  are best for seeing the “Big Picture,” namely the general, the  forest — say, the meaning of our job. As modern people rush  around blowing small problems out of proportion, thus  contributing to a global anxiety epidemic, ancestral spirits  have a broader perspective that can                        .  When it comes to a trivial problem, for example, they’ll just  tell us, “This too will pass.” They appreciate how rapidly and  often things change. According to American anthropologist  Richard Katz, for instance, Fijians say that from the  ancestral viewpoint whatever looks unfortunate may turn out  to be fortunate after all: “What may seem to be a horrible  outcome ... is seen in another light by the ancestors.” The  ancestors, it might be said, keep their heads when everyone  around them is losing theirs. * epidemic: 확산  ** anthropologist: 인류학자",
        "choices": [
            "calm the disquieted soul",
            "boost cooperation in the community",
            "make us stick to the specific details",
            "result in a waste of time",
            "complicate situations"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "question": "One of the criticisms of Stoicism by modern translators and  teachers is the amount of repetition. Marcus Aurelius, for  example, has been dismissed by academics as not being  original because his writing resembles that of other, earlier  Stoics. This criticism misses the point. Even before Marcus’s  time, Seneca was well aware that there was a lot of  borrowing and overlap among the philosophers. That’s because  real philosophers weren’t concerned with authorship, but only  what worked. More important, they believed that what was  said mattered less than what was done. And this is true now  as it was then. You’re welcome to take all of the words of  the great philosophers and use them to your own liking  (they’re dead; they don’t mind). Feel free to make  adjustments and improvements as you like. Adapt them to the  real conditions of the real world. The way to prove that you  truly understand what you speak and write, that you truly are  original, is to                                . [3점] * Stoicism: 스토아 철학",
        "choices": [
            "put them into practice",
            "keep your writings to yourself",
            "combine oral and written traditions",
            "compare philosophical theories",
            "avoid borrowing them"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "question": "다음 글에서 전체 흐름과 관계 없는 문장은? Several common themes were found in the highly creative  individuals regarding their early experiences and education. In  early childhood their families accorded them a great deal of  respect and allowed them to explore on their own and  develop a strong sense of personal autonomy.",
        "choices": [
            "There was \nalso a lack of extreme emotional closeness with parents.",
            "There \nwas \nlittle \nevidence \nof \nintensely \nnegative \nexperiences; for example there was, relative to the times in \nwhich they lived, very little physical punishment for \ntransgressions. 3. Nor, on the positive side, was there \nevidence of extremely intense bonds of the sort that can \nsmother independence. 4. There was more competition among \nbrothers and sisters for parental love in nuclear families than \nin extended families. 5. On balance, for those who would \ngrow up to be highly creative, relationships with parents \nwere relatively easy and, in later life, pleasant and friendly \nrather than intensely intimate.\n* autonomy: 자율성  ** transgression: 일탈  *** smother: 억누르다\n[36 ~ 37] 주어진 글 다음에 이어질 글의 순서로 가장 적절한 것을 \n고르시오."
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "question": "Shakespeare wrote, “What’s in a name? That which we  call a rose by any other name would smell as sweet.” (A) Take the word bridge. In German, bridge (die brücke) is  a feminine noun; in Spanish, bridge (el puente) is a  masculine noun. Boroditsky found that when asked to  describe a bridge, native German speakers used words  like beautiful, elegant, slender. When native Spanish  speakers were asked the same question, they used  words like strong, sturdy, towering.  (B) According to Stanford University psychology professor  Lera Boroditsky, that’s not necessarily so. Focusing on  the grammatical gender differences between German and  Spanish, Boroditsky’s work indicates that the gender our  language assigns to a given noun influences us to  subconsciously give that noun characteristics of the  grammatical gender.  (C) This worked the other way around as well. The word  key is masculine in German and feminine in Spanish.  When asked to describe a key, native German speakers  used words like jagged, heavy, hard, metal. Spanish  speakers used words like intricate, golden, lovely. * jagged: 뾰족뾰족한  ** intricate: 정교한",
        "choices": [
            "(A) - (C) - (B)",
            "(B) - (A) - (C)",
            "(B) - (C) - (A)",
            "(C) - (A) - (B)",
            "(C) - (B) - (A)\n\n고3\n영어영역\n7\n7\n8"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "question": "Our perception always involves some imagination. It is  more similar to painting than to photography. And,  according to the confirmation effect, we blindly trust the  reality we construct. (A) You will see that the majority of us are quite ignorant  about what lies around us. This is not so puzzling. The  most extraordinary fact is that we completely disregard  this ignorance. (B) This is best witnessed in visual illusions, which we  perceive with full confidence, as if there were no doubt  that we are portraying reality faithfully. One interesting  way of discovering this — in a simple game that can be  played at any moment — is the following.  (C) Whenever you are with another person, ask him or her  to close their eyes, and start asking questions about  what is nearby — not very particular details but the most  striking elements of the scene. What is the color of the  wall? Is there a table in the room? Does that man have  a beard? [3점]",
        "choices": [
            "(A) - (C) - (B)",
            "(B) - (A) - (C)",
            "(B) - (C) - (A)",
            "(C) - (A) - (B)",
            "(C) - (B) - (A)\n[38 ~ 39] 글의 흐름으로 보아, 주어진 문장이 들어가기에 가장 \n적절한 곳을 고르시오."
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "question": "But when students were given “worked­examples” (such  as pre­solved problems) placed between problems to  solve, studying the worked­examples freed up cognitive  resources that allowed students to see the key features  of the problem and to analyze the steps and reasons  behind problem­solving moves. How can we help students manage cognitive load as they  learn to perform complex tasks? One method that has proved  effective in research studies is to support some aspects of a  complex task while students perform the entire task. (",
        "choices": [
            ") For \nexample, Swelter and Cooper demonstrated this with students \nlearning to solve problems in a variety of quantitative fields \nfrom statistics to physics. ( 2. ) They found that when \nstudents were given typical word problems, it was possible \nfor them to solve the problems without actually learning \nmuch. ( 3. ) This is because the problems themselves were \nsufficiently demanding that students had no cognitive resources \navailable to learn from what they did. ( 4. ) The researchers \nfound this improved students’ performance on subsequent \nproblem solving. ( 5. ) This result, called the worked­example \neffect, is one example of a process called scaffolding, by which \ninstructors temporarily relieve some of the cognitive load so that \nstudents can focus on particular dimensions of learning. [3점]\n* word problem: 문장제(이야기 형식으로 제시된 문제)\n** scaffolding: 발판 놓기"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "question": "In contrast, the other major advocate of utilitarianism, John  Stuart Mill, argued for a more qualitative approach, assuming  that there can be different subjective levels of pleasure. Utilitarian ethics argues that all action should be directed  toward achieving the greatest total amount of happiness for the  largest number of people. (",
        "choices": [
            ") Utilitarian ethics assumes that \nall actions can be evaluated in terms of their moral worth, and \nso the desirability of an action is determined by its resulting \nhedonistic \nconsequences. ( 2. ) This \nis \na \nconsequentialist \ncreed, assuming that the moral value and desirability of an action \ncan be determined from its likely outcomes. ( 3. ) Jeremy \nBentham suggested that the value of hedonistic outcomes can \nbe quantitatively assessed, so that the value of consequent \npleasure can be derived by multiplying its intensity and its \nduration. ( 4. ) Higher­quality pleasures are more desirable than \nlower­quality \npleasures. ( 5. ) Less \nsophisticated \ncreatures \n(like pigs!) have an easier access to the simpler pleasures, but \nmore sophisticated creatures like humans have the capacity to \naccess higher pleasures and should be motivated to seek those. \n* utilitarianism: 공리주의  ** hedonistic: 쾌락적인  *** creed: 신조"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "question": "다음 글의 내용을 한 문장으로 요약하고자 한다. 빈칸 (A),  (B)에 들어갈 말로 가장 적절한 것은? Music has no past; it exists only at the moment when  it happens, and no two performances are identical. This is  music’s greatest asset because it brings out the essential  ‘now’ without implications of a past and a potential future.  Thus, Stravinsky pointed out that only through music are  we able to ‘realize the present.’ Musical ‘meaning’ cannot  be separated from the act of presentation. However, the  necessity of present­ing music — making it present here  and now, without which it will not be music at all — does  not sit easily with a concept of education that rests  mainly upon received factual knowledge and which, by  tradition, uses the past to make sense of the present. If  we want music to have a role in general education, it  would seem logical to acknowledge this difference and  give prominence to activities that will involve all pupils  working directly with music. Yet, in spite of numerous  attempts to develop a more musical music curriculum for  the majority of school pupils, the emphasis is still on  pupils absorbing factual information about music.   Music’s quality of being in the present is  (A)  in  formal  music  education,  where  delivering  factual  knowledge is  (B) . (A)  (B)",
        "choices": [
            "overlooked\n······\nprioritized",
            "overlooked\n······\nrestricted",
            "dismissed\n······\ndisregarded",
            "achieved\n······\ntreasured",
            "achieved\n······\nchallenged\n\n8\n영어영역\n고3\n8\n8\n[41 ~ 42] 다음 글을 읽고, 물음에 답하시오.\nThe domination of nature is a familiar trope in \nenvironmental ethics and environmental political theory. \nIts history is tied more broadly to the rise of modern \nscience, philosophy, and politics. The effort to understand \nthe causal relations that govern the physical world so as \nto intervene in these relations in ways that could, as \nFrancis Bacon put it, “ameliorate the human condition,” \nmarked the beginning of modernity in the West. For a \nlong time, the “domination of nature” referred to this \neffort to understand and (a) control the nonhuman \nenvironment, and it was seen as a clearly good thing. \nThis effort made (b) possible new technologies and rising \neconomic prosperity, promised an end to many forms of \nhuman suffering, and demonstrated the triumph of reason \nover ignorance and superstition. Its costs began to be \n(c) invisible \nwith \nindustrialization \nin \nthe \nnineteenth \ncentury, which generated obvious environmental damage \nand caused among many people a sense of alienation \nfrom the land and the more­than­human communities \ncomposing it. One sees a growing (d) unease about these \ncosts in novels of the era such as Mary Shelley’s \nFrankenstein \n(1818), \nin \npoems \nlike \nWordsworth’s \n“Michael” (1800) and later Whitman’s Leaves of Grass \n(1855), and in the early nature writing of Thoreau’s \nWalden (1854). Yet systematic, critical analysis of the \ndomination of nature as a problem came into its own \nonly with the environmental studies movement in the \n1970s. Since then, the trope has come to have a broadly \n(e) negative meaning, with the domination of nature being \nviewed as harmful and illegitimate, as well as dangerous \nto human interests. \n* trope: 수사적 표현  ** ameliorate: 개선하다"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "question": "윗글의 제목으로 가장 적절한 것은?",
        "choices": [
            "Changing Perspectives on the Domination of Nature",
            "Science Starts from a Desire for Knowledge",
            "Ethics Is Central to Every Discipline",
            "Nature in Literature Is Not Real",
            "Is Going Green Really Green?"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "question": "밑줄 친 (a)~(e) 중에서 문맥상 낱말의 쓰임이 적절하지 않은  것은?",
        "choices": [
            "(a)",
            "(b)",
            "(c)",
            "(d)",
            "(e)\n[43 ~ 45] 다음 글을 읽고, 물음에 답하시오.\n(A)\nIn a peaceful town surrounded by rolling hills, there \nlived a kind­hearted young woman named Emily. She had \na strong desire to make a difference in the world, yet \noften felt that her efforts were insignificant. One day, \nEmily crossed paths with Martha, an elderly lady known \nfor (a) her sour mood and tendency to keep to herself. \nCuriosity sparked within Emily, prompting her to initiate \na conversation with Martha.\n(B)\nThe event showcased the great works of many local \nartists, with a special surprise awaiting Martha. Emily had \ncarefully \nprepared \na \nsection \ndedicated \nto \nMartha’s \npaintings, hoping to unveil it to her and the community. \nThe day of the exhibition arrived, and the townspeople \neagerly gathered, excited to witness the artistic wonders \nof their community. Emily anxiously awaited Martha’s \narrival, wondering how Martha would react to the surprise \n(b) she had planned. Martha finally entered the exhibition \nhall, and her eyes filled with tears as she stood in front \nof her own artworks.\n(C)\nMartha slowly made her way through the section \ndedicated to (c) her paintings, examining each piece with \na mix of nostalgia and longing. The crowd watched in \nsilence, their hearts touched by Martha’s emotional \nresponse. As Martha reached the last painting, she turned \nto Emily with a bright smile, tears still shining in her \neyes. “Emily, you’ve given me back a part of myself that \nI thought was lost forever,” Martha whispered, (d) her \nvoice shaking with gratitude. “I had forgotten the joy that \nart once brought me, but you’ve reminded me of its \npower.” \n(D)\nDespite Martha’s initial resistance, Emily persistently \nreached out to her, sharing stories and expressing genuine \ninterest in (e) her life. Through their conversations, Emily \ndiscovered that Martha had once been a famous painter. \nHowever, she had lost her passion for art due to personal \nhardships. Deeply moved by her sorrow, Emily resolved to \nhelp revive Martha’s creative spirit. So, she organized an \nart exhibition in the town’s community center."
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "question": "주어진 글 (A)에 이어질 내용을 순서에 맞게 배열한 것으로  가장 적절한 것은?",
        "choices": [
            "(B) - (D) - (C)",
            "(C) - (B) - (D)",
            "(C) - (D) - (B)",
            "(D) - (B) - (C)",
            "(D) - (C) - (B)"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "question": "밑줄 친 (a)~(e) 중에서 가리키는 대상이 나머지 넷과 다른 것은?",
        "choices": [
            "(a)",
            "(b)",
            "(c)",
            "(d)",
            "(e)"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "question": "윗글에 관한 내용으로 적절하지 않은 것은?",
        "choices": [
            "Emily는 호기심이 생겨 Martha와 대화를 시작하게 되었다.",
            "미술 전시회에서는 Martha의 작품만 전시했다.",
            "마을 사람들은 Martha의 반응을 보고 마음이 뭉클했다.",
            "Martha는 마지막 그림에 이르러 Emily를 향해 미소를 지었다.",
            "Martha는 개인적인 역경 때문에 미술에 대한 열정을 잃었다.\n* 확인 사항\n◦답안지의 해당란에 필요한 내용을 정확히 기입(표기)\n했는지 확인하시오."
        ],
        "answer": 2
    }
]